<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michał Chromiak's blog - Sequence Models</title><link href="https://mchromiak.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/sequence-models.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mchromiak.github.io/</id><updated>2017-11-30T19:30:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>NLP: Explaining Neural Language Modeling</title><link href="https://mchromiak.github.io/articles/2017/Nov/30/Explaining-Neural-Language-Modeling/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-30T19:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-30T19:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Michał Chromiak</name></author><id>tag:mchromiak.github.io,2017-11-30:/articles/2017/Nov/30/Explaining-Neural-Language-Modeling/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Language modeling (LM) is the essential part of Natural Language Processing (NLP) tasks such as  Machine Translation, Spell Correction Speech Recognition, Summarization, Question Answering, Sentiment analysis etc. Goal of the Language Model is to compute the probability of sentence considered as a word sequence. This article explains how to model the language using probability and n-grams. It also discuss the language model evaluation with  use of &lt;em&gt;perplexity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read before:&lt;/strong&gt;
* &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@gon.esbuyo/get-started-with-nlp-part-i-d67ca26cc828"&gt;Get started with NLP (Part I)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Takeaways:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The goal of a language model is to compute a probability of a token (e.g. a sentence or a sequence of words).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language Model (LM) actually a grammar of a language as it gives the probability of word that will follow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dictionary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corpus&lt;/strong&gt; - Body of text, singular. Corpora is the plural of this. Example: A collection of medical journals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Token&lt;/strong&gt;- Each "entity" that is a part of whatever was split up based on rules. For examples, each word is a token when a sentence is "tokenized" into words. Each sentence can also be a token, if you tokenized the sentences out of a paragraph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lexicon&lt;/strong&gt; - Words and their meanings. Example: English dictionary. Consider, however, that various fields will have different lexicons. For example: To a financial investor, the first meaning for thef word "Bull" is someone who is confident about the market, as compared to the common English lexicon, where the first meaning for the word "Bull" is an animal. As such, there is a special lexicon for financial investors, doctors, children, mechanics, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="intro"&gt;Intro&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#intro" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Language Modeling (LM)&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important parts of modern Natural Language Processing (NLP). There are many sorts of applications for  Language Modeling, like: Machine Translation, Spell Correction Speech Recognition, Summarization, Question Answering, Sentiment analysis etc. Each of those tasks require use of &lt;em&gt;language model&lt;/em&gt;. Language model is required to represent the text to a form understandable from the machine point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I have elaborated on the means to model a corpus of text to use in multiple machine learning NLP tasks.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="motivation"&gt;Motivation&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#motivation" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each part of natural language has to assume some representation. Written text in natural way is composed out of sentences that consist of words that in turn contains letters. Each of those pieces of  text sentence can be a subject for analysis. Of course we can also use morphemes [ref]Small meaningful units that make up words. [\ref] or n-grams of the text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way or another, the text needs to be normalized.  Normalized mean that indexed text and query terms must have same form. For example, &lt;em&gt;U.S.A.&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;u.s.a.&lt;/em&gt; are to be considered same (remove dots and case fold - lowercase) and return same result while querying any of them.  Thus, an implicit word classes equivalence must be defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="tokenizing"&gt;Tokenizing&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#tokenizing" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing which text segmentation (aka tokenizing) technique will be used is arbitrary, but depends strictly on the undergoing tasks, their specification, heuristics and preconditions. For instance, if we are after a single character statistics of text task we will probably choose to operate on letters not on n-grams or words. The result for text fragmentation is called &lt;strong&gt;token&lt;/strong&gt;. So by referring to a token in general one actually refers to the fragmentation technique outcome in form of a sentence, word, n-gram, morpheme, letter etc.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even word-oriented tokens might give a different set of distinct tokens. For instance in a lemma based tokens the &lt;em&gt;cat&lt;/em&gt; and plural &lt;em&gt;cats&lt;/em&gt; would count as one word having same stem (core meaning-bearing unit). On the other hand, if we make more strict distinctions, that would e.g. differentiate &lt;em&gt;word form&lt;/em&gt;, we would get two distinct tokens. It all depends how you define a token.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make things more clear, lets settle three terms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vocabulary&lt;/strong&gt; set of different types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;type&lt;/strong&gt;  an element of vocabulary, and a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;token&lt;/strong&gt; as an instance of a &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, language modeling must consider the correlated ordering of tokens. This is because every language is based on some grammar, where order has a lot of influence on the meaning of a text.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To complete the NLP tasks we must provide a measure to enable comparison operations and thus assessment method for grading our model. This measure is probability. This involves all kinds of tasks, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine translation:&lt;/strong&gt; translating a sentence saying about height it would probably state that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( P(tall\ man) &amp;gt; P(large\ man)\)&lt;/span&gt; as the ‘&lt;em&gt;large&lt;/em&gt;’ might also refer to weight or general appearance thus, not as probable as ‘&lt;em&gt;tall&lt;/em&gt;’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spelling Correction:&lt;/strong&gt;  Spell correcting sentence: “Put you name into form”, so that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(name\ into\ \textbf{form}) &amp;gt; P(name\ into\ \textbf{from})\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speech Recognition:&lt;/strong&gt; Call my nurse: &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(Call\ my\ nurse.) \gg P(coal\ miners)\)&lt;/span&gt;, I have no idea. &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(no\ idea.) \gg P(No\ eye\ deer.)\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summarization, question answering, sentiment analysis&lt;/strong&gt; etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-probabilistic-language-modeling"&gt;The probabilistic language modeling&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#the-probabilistic-language-modeling" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probability of a sentence &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(S\)&lt;/span&gt; (as a sequence of &lt;em&gt;words&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w_i\)&lt;/span&gt;) is : &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(S) = P(w_1,w_2, w_3,\ldots,w_n)\)&lt;/span&gt;. Now it is important to find the probability of upcoming word. It is an everyday task made e.g. while typing  your mobile keyboard. We will settle the &lt;em&gt;conditional probability&lt;/em&gt;  of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w_4\)&lt;/span&gt; depending on all previous words. For a 4 word sentence this conditional probability is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ P(S)=P(w_1, w_2, w_3, w_4) \equiv P(w_4 |w_1, w_2, w3) $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way we can actually represent the language grammar, however, in NLP it is accustomed to use the LM term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To calculate the joint probability  of a sentence (as a word sequence) &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(W)\)&lt;/span&gt; the chain rule of probability will be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Probability Chain Rule:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P(A|B) = \frac{P(A\cap B)}{P(B)} \implies P(A\cap B)=P(A|B)P(B)$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so in general for a token sequence we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P(S)=P(w_1,\ldots,w_n) = P(w_1)P(w_2|w_1) P(w_3)P(w_1,w_2)\ldots P(w_n|w_1,\ldots w_{n-1}) ={\displaystyle \prod_{i} P(w_i|w_1,\ldots w_{i-1})}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To estimate each probability a straightforward solution could be to use simple counting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P(w_5|w_1,w_2,w_3,w_4)= \frac{count(w_1,w_2,w_3,w_4,w_5)}{count(w_1,w_2,w_3,w_4)}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but this gives us to many possible sequences to ever estimate. Imagine how much data (occurrences of each sentence) we would have to get to make this &lt;em&gt;count&lt;/em&gt;s meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To cope with this issue we can simplify by applying the &lt;strong&gt;Markov Assumption&lt;/strong&gt;, which states that it is enough to pick only one, or a couple of previous words as a prefix:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P(w_1,\ldots,w_n) \approx {\displaystyle \prod_{i} P(w_i|w_{i-k},\ldots P(w_{i-1}))}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt; is the number of previous tokens (&lt;em&gt;prefix&lt;/em&gt; size) that we consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="n-grams"&gt;N-grams&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#n-grams" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An N-gram is a contiguous (order matters) sequence of items, which in this case is the words in text. The n-grams depends on the size of the &lt;em&gt;prefix&lt;/em&gt;. The simplest case is the &lt;em&gt;Unigram mode&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; (Uni-) 1-gram model&lt;/strong&gt;
The simplest case of &lt;em&gt;Markov assumption&lt;/em&gt; is case when the size of prefix is one.
&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(w_1,\ldots,w_n) \approx {\displaystyle \prod_{i} P(w_i)}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will provide us with grammar that only consider one word. As a result it produces a set of unrelated words. It actually would generate sentences with random word order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Bigram &lt;/strong&gt;
However, if we consider a 2-word (tandem) bigrams correlations where we condition each word on previous one we get some sens of meaning between couples of words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P(w_1,\ldots,w_n) \approx {\displaystyle \prod_{i} P(w_i|w_{i-1})}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way we get a sequence of tandems that have meaning tandem-wise. This still is not enough to face a long range dependencies from natural languages, like English. This would be difficult even in case of n-grams as there can be very long sentences with dependencies. However, a 3-gram can get us a pretty nice &lt;a href="http://tetration.xyz/Ngram-Tutorial/"&gt;approximation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;and how he probably more easily believe me i never see how much as that he and pride and unshackled
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4 id="estimate-n-gram-probabilities"&gt;Estimate n-gram probabilities&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#estimate-n-gram-probabilities" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimation can be done with &lt;strong&gt;Maximum Likelihood Estimate (MLE)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P(w_i|w_{i-1})=\frac{count(w_{i-1},w_i)}{count(w_{i-1 })}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- z jupytera:
Z google ngram raw bigram count table
normalize by unigrams --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the 2-gram estimate  of sentence probability would be the product of all component tandems ordered as in the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P(w_1,\ldots,w_n) \approx {\displaystyle \prod_{i} P(w_i|w_{i-1})}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, the outcome should be represented in &lt;em&gt;log&lt;/em&gt; form. There are two reasons for this. Firstly, if the sentence is long and the probabilities are really small, then such product might end in arithmetic underflow.  Secondly, adding is faster - and when we use logarithm we know that: &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(log(a*b) = log(a)+log(b)\)&lt;/span&gt;, thus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(log(P(w_1,\ldots,w_n)) \approx {\displaystyle \sum_{i} log(P(w_i|w_{i-1}))}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why the Language Model is stored in logarithmic values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="publicly-available-corpora"&gt;Publicly available corpora&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#publicly-available-corpora" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is available &lt;a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/search/"&gt;Gutenberg Project&lt;/a&gt; providing with text format of some books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google also released a publicly available corpus trillion word corpus with over 13 million unique words. It is nice corpus from Google Books with already implemented &lt;a href="https://books.google.com/ngrams"&gt;N-Gram viewer&lt;/a&gt; that enables to plot word counts. It includes number of corpora for multiple languages. See the below chart an example of unigram, 2-gram and 3-gram occurrences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe name="ngram_chart" src="https://books.google.com/ngrams/interactive_chart?content=machine+learning%2Cdeep+learning%2Cnlp%2Cnatural+language+processing&amp;year_start=1982&amp;year_end=2008&amp;corpus=0&amp;smoothing=3&amp;share=&amp;direct_url=t1%3B%2Cmachine%20learning%3B%2Cc0%3B.t1%3B%2Cdeep%20learning%3B%2Cc0%3B.t1%3B%2Cnlp%3B%2Cc0%3B.t1%3B%2Cnatural%20language%20processing%3B%2Cc0" width=860 height=300 marginwidth=0 marginheight=0 hspace=0 vspace=0 frameborder=0 scrolling=no&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a large scale text analysis can be done by downloading &lt;a href="http://storage.googleapis.com/books/ngrams/books/datasetsv2.html"&gt;each dataset&lt;/a&gt; using the &lt;a href="https://books.google.com/ngrams/info"&gt;Ngram Viewer API&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have created a project to collect and analyze those datasets locally with custom configuration. See the &lt;a href="https://github.com/MChromiak/MC_Utils"&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; for the source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="language-model-evaluation-perplexity"&gt;Language Model evaluation – Perplexity&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#language-model-evaluation-perplexity" title="Permanent link"&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good LM should calculate higher probabilities to “real” and “frequently observed” sentences than the ones that are wrong accordingly to natural language grammar or those that are rarely observed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make such assumption, we first train the language model on one set and test it on completely new dataset. Then we can compare the results of our model on the new dataset and evaluate, how good (how accurate in terms of a task e.g. translation, spell check etc) &lt;strong&gt;on average&lt;/strong&gt; it works on this new, previously unseen dataset. For instance how many words it translates correctly. This way one can compare and decide which language model fits the best to a task. This is called &lt;em&gt;extrinsic evaluation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extrinsic evaluation approach however, requires multiple tests on models which are expensive. An alternative is the &lt;em&gt;intrinsic evaluation&lt;/em&gt; which is about testing the LM itself not some particular task or application. The popular intrinsic evaluation is &lt;strong&gt;perplexity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;strong&gt;perplexity&lt;/strong&gt; is a bad approximation to an extreme extrinsic evaluation, in cases where the test dataset does NOT look just like the training set. Thus, it is useful only at the early stages of experiment. So later in experiment extrinsic evaluation should also be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best model is the one that best predicts an unseen test set, or assigns on average the probability to all sentences that is sees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perprexity metric is the probability of the test set, normalized for the length of the probability by the number of words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ PP(S) = P(w_1,\ldots, w_N)^{-\frac{1}{N}} =\sqrt[\leftroot{0}\uproot{3}N]{\frac{1}{P(w_1,\ldots, w_N)}} = $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way the longer the sentence the less probable it will be. Then again by the chain rule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ = \sqrt[N]{{\displaystyle \prod_{i}^{N}\frac{1}{P(w_i|w_1,\ldots, w_{i-1})}}} $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of 2-gram using Markov approximation of the chain rule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ PP(S) =  \sqrt[N]{{\displaystyle \prod_{i}^{N}\frac{1}{P(w_i|w_{i-1})}}}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;perplexity&lt;/em&gt; is a function of probability of the sentence. The meaning of the inversion in perplexity means that whenever we minimize the perplexity we maximize the probability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perplexity is weighted equivalent branching factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be continued...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="NLP"></category><category term="language model"></category><category term="ngram"></category><category term="perplexity"></category><category term="smoothing"></category></entry><entry><title>The Transformer – Attention is all you need.</title><link href="https://mchromiak.github.io/articles/2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-12T19:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-30T19:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Michał Chromiak</name></author><id>tag:mchromiak.github.io,2017-09-12:/articles/2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Transformer - more than meets the eye! Are we there yet? Well... not really, but...&lt;/br&gt;   How about eliminating recurrence and convolution from transduction? Sequence modeling and transduction (e.g. language modeling, machine translation) problems solutions has been dominated by RNN (especially gated RNN) or LSTM, additionally employing the attention mechanism. Main sequence transduction models are based on RNN or CNN including encoder and decoder. The new &lt;em&gt;transformer&lt;/em&gt; architecture is claimed however, to be more parallelizable and requiring significantly less time to train, solely focusing on attention mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h5 id=recommended-reading-before-approaching-this-post&gt;Recommended reading before approaching this post:&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#recommended-reading-before-approaching-this-post&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RNN – Andrej Karpathy’s blog &lt;a href="http://karpathy.github.io/2015/05/21/rnn-effectiveness/"&gt;The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Recurrent Neural Networks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seq2Seq - Nathan Lintz &lt;a href="https://indico.io/blog/sequence-modeling-neuralnets-part1/"&gt;Sequence Modeling With Neural Networks (Part 1): Language &amp;amp; Seq2Seq&lt;/a&gt;,
Part2 &lt;a href="https://indico.io/blog/sequence-modeling-neural-networks-part2-attention-models/"&gt;Sequence modeling with attention&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LSTM – Christopher Olah’s blog &lt;a href="http://colah.github.io/posts/2015-08-Understanding-LSTMs/"&gt;Understanding LSTM Networks&lt;/a&gt; and R2Rt.com &lt;a href="https://r2rt.com/written-memories-understanding-deriving-and-extending-the-lstm.html"&gt;Written Memories: Understanding, Deriving and Extending the LSTM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attention – Christopher Olah &lt;a href="https://distill.pub/2016/augmented-rnns/#attentional-interfaces"&gt;Attention and Augmented Recurrent Neural Networks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=objective-or-goal-for-the-algorithm&gt;Objective or goal for the algorithm&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#objective-or-goal-for-the-algorithm&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parallelization of Seq2Seq:&lt;/strong&gt; RNN/CNN handle sequences word-by-word sequentially which is an obstacle to parallelize. Transformer achieve parallelization by replacing recurrence with attention and encoding the symbol position in sequence. This in turn leads to significantly shorter training time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce sequential computation:&lt;/strong&gt; Constant &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(1)\)&lt;/span&gt; number of operations to learn dependency between two symbols independently of their position distance in sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=tldr&gt;TL;DR&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#tldr&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RNN:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages:&lt;/strong&gt; are popular and successful for variable-length representations such as sequences (e.g. languages), images, etc. RNN are considered core of seq2seq (with attention). The gating models such as LSTM or GRU are for long-range error propagation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problems:&lt;/strong&gt; The sequentiality prohibits parallelization within instances. Long-range dependencies still tricky, despite gating.  Sequence-aligned states in RNN are wasteful. Hard to model hierarchical-alike domains such as languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CNN:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages:&lt;/strong&gt; Trivial to parallelize (per layer) and fit intuition that most dependencies are local.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problems:&lt;/strong&gt; Path length between positions can be logarithmic when using dilated convolutions, left-padding for text. (autoregressive CNNs WaveNet, ByteNET )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution:&lt;/strong&gt; Multi-head self-attention mechanism. Why attention? Table 2 of the paper shows that such attention networks can save 2–3 orders of magnitude of operations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=intro&gt;Intro&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#intro&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will elaborate on lately presented paper introducing the &lt;strong&gt;Transformer&lt;/strong&gt; architecture.
Paper: &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03762"&gt;ArXiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the paper assumes the in-depth prior knowledge of some topics, I will try to explain the ideas of the paper so that they can be understood by a DL beginner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When RNN’s (or CNN) takes a sequence as an input, it handles sentences word by word. This sequentiality  is an obstacle toward parallelization of the process. What is more, in cases when such sequences are too long, the model is prone to forgetting the content of distant positions in sequence or mix it with following positions’ content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution to this was Convolution seq2seq. Convolution enables parallelization for GPU processing. Thus &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03122"&gt;Gehring et al, 2017&lt;/a&gt; (Facebook AI) present a 100% convolutional architecture to represent hierarchical representation of input sequence. The crux is that close input elements interact at lower layers while distant interacts at higher layers. The stacking of convolution layers is being used to evaluate long range dependencies between words. This is all possible despite fixed width kernels of convolution filters. The authors has also included two tricks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positional embeddings - that are added to the input embeddings, capturing a sense of order in a sequence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-step attention - attention is computed with current decoder state and embedding of previous target word token&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img src="https://mchromiak.github.io/articles/2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/img/MultiStepAttention.gif" alt="Multi-step attention "&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Figure 1. Multi-step attention form ConvS2S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative to convolutions, a new approach is presented by the &lt;em&gt;Transformer&lt;/em&gt;. It proposes to encode each position and applying the attention mechanism, to relate two distant words, which then can be parallelized thus, accelerating the training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, in NLP the SOTA (&lt;em&gt;state-of-the-art&lt;/em&gt;) performance achieved by seq2seq models is focused around the idea of encoding the input sentence into a fixed-size vector representation. The vector size is fixed, regardless of the length of the input sentence. In obvious way this must loose some information. To face this issue &lt;em&gt;Transformer&lt;/em&gt; employs an alternative approach based on attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to multiple referred work it is beneficial to also read the mentioned research&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.03906"&gt;Denny Britz on Attention, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.04304"&gt;Self-attention (a.k.a Intra-attention), 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=motivation&gt;Motivation&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#motivation&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Transformer architecture is aimed at the problem of &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1211.3711"&gt;&lt;em&gt;sequence transduction&lt;/em&gt; (by Alex Graves)&lt;/a&gt;, meaning any task where input sequences are transformed into output sequences. This includes speech recognition, text-to-speech transformation, machine translation, protein secondary structure prediction, Turing machines etc. Basically the goal is to design a single framework to handle as many sequences as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, complex RNN and CNN based on encoder-decoder scheme are dominating transduction models (language modeling and machine learning). Recurrent models due to sequential nature (computations focused on the position of symbol in input and output) are not allowing for parallelization along training, thus have a problem with learning long-term dependencies (&lt;a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/articleDetails.jsp?reload=true&amp;amp;arnumber=5264952"&gt;Hochreiter,, et  al.&lt;/a&gt;) from memory. The bigger the memory is, the better, but the memory eventually  constrains batching across learning examples for long sequences, and this is why parallelization can not help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reducing this fundamental constraint of sequential computation has been target for numerous research like &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1609.03499"&gt;Wavenet&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1610.10099"&gt;Bytenet&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03122"&gt;ConvS2S&lt;/a&gt;. However, in those CNN-based approaches, the number of calculations in parallel computation of the hidden representation, for input&lt;span class=math&gt;\(\rightarrow\)&lt;/span&gt;output position in sequence, grows with the distance between those positions. The complexity of &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(n)\)&lt;/span&gt; for ConvS2S and  &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(nlogn)\)&lt;/span&gt; for ByteNet makes it harder to learn dependencies on distant positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformer reduces the number of sequential operations to relate two symbols from input/output sequences  to a constant &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(1)\)&lt;/span&gt; number of operations. Transformer achieves this with the &lt;em&gt;multi-head attention&lt;/em&gt; mechanism that allows to model dependencies regardless of their distance in input or output sentence.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up till now, most of the research including attention is used along with RNNs. The novel approach of Transformer is however, to eliminate recurrence completely and replace it with attention to handle the dependencies between input and output. The Transformer moves the sweet spot of current ideas toward attention entirely. It eliminates the not only recurrence but also convolution in favor of applying &lt;strong&gt;self-attention&lt;/strong&gt; (a.k.a intra-attention). Additionally Transformer gives more space for parallelization (details present in paper).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top performance in the paper is achieved while applying the &lt;strong&gt;attention&lt;/strong&gt; mechanism connecting encoder and decoder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformer is claimed by authors to be the first to rely entirely on self-attention to compute representations of input and output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=information-on-processing-strategy-of-the-algorithm&gt;Information on processing strategy of the algorithm&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#information-on-processing-strategy-of-the-algorithm&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformer is based on sequence-to-sequence model for &lt;em&gt;Statistical Machine Translation&lt;/em&gt; (SMT) as introduced in &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1406.1078"&gt;Cho et al., 2014&lt;/a&gt;. It includes two RNNs, one for &lt;strong&gt;encoder&lt;/strong&gt; to process the input and the other as a &lt;strong&gt;decoder&lt;/strong&gt;, for generating the output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, transformer’s &lt;em&gt;encoder&lt;/em&gt; maps input sequence to its continuous representation &lt;span class=math&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; which in turn is used by &lt;em&gt;decoder&lt;/em&gt; to generate output, one symbol at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final state of the encoder is a fixed size vector &lt;span class=math&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; that must encode entire source sentence which includes the sentence meaning. This final state is therefore called &lt;em&gt;sentence embedding&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-1-back&gt;&lt;a title="While applying dimensionality reduction techniques (e.g. PCA, t-SNE) on embeddings, the outcome plot gathers the semantically close sentences  together Sutskever et al., 2014." class=simple-footnote href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-1&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The encoder-decoder model is designed at its each step to be &lt;strong&gt;auto-regressive&lt;/strong&gt; -  i.e. use previously generated  symbols as extra input while generating next symbol. Thus, &lt;span class=math&gt;\( x_i + y_{i-1}\rightarrow y_i\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=transformer-is-based-on-encoder-decoder&gt;Transformer is based on Encoder-Decoder&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#transformer-is-based-on-encoder-decoder&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Transformer (as in ByteNet or ConvS2S) the &lt;em&gt;decoder&lt;/em&gt; is stacked directly on top of &lt;em&gt;encoder&lt;/em&gt;. Encoder and decoder both are composed of stack of identical layers. Each of those stacked layers is composed out of two general types of sub-layers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;multi-head self-attention mechanism, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;position-wise fully connected FFN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to ConvS2S however, where input representation considered each input element  combined with its absolute position number in sequence (providing sense of ordering; ByteNet have dilated convolutions and no position-wise FNN), transformer introduces two different NN for these two types of information.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way the attention mechanism is applied and customized is what makes the Transformer novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can find the reference Transformer model implementation from authors is present in &lt;a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tensor2tensor/blob/master/tensor2tensor/models/transformer.py"&gt;Tensor2Tensor (T2T) library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img src="https://mchromiak.github.io/articles/2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/img/encoder.png" alt="Encoder Decoder architecture "&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Figure 2. Single layer of Encoder (left) and Decoder (right) that is build out of &lt;span class=math&gt;\(N=6\)&lt;/span&gt; identical layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=encoder&gt;Encoder&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#encoder&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 1 – Encoder Input&lt;/strong&gt;
Information on sequence ordering is very important. As there is no recurrence, nor convolution, this information on absolute (or relative) position of each token in a sequence is represented with use of "&lt;em&gt;positional encodings&lt;/em&gt;"
(&lt;a href="../../../../2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/#positional-encoding-pe"&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;). The input for the encoder is therefore, represented  as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;positional encodings&lt;/em&gt;  added &lt;span class=math&gt;\(\oplus\)&lt;/span&gt; to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;embedded inputs&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=math&gt;\(N=6\)&lt;/span&gt; layers. In practice the &lt;span class=math&gt;\(N=6\)&lt;/span&gt; means more than 6 layers. Each of those “layers” are actually composed of two layers: position-wise FNN and one (encoder), or two (decoder), attention-based sublayers. Each of those additionally contains 4 linear projections and the attention logic. Thus, providing effectively deeper than 6 layer architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 2 – Multi-head attention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 3 – position-wise FFN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stages 2 and 3 use the residual connection (thus, all employ &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_{model}=512\)&lt;/span&gt;) followed by normalization layer at its output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, encoder works like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=highlight&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Stage1_out = Embedding512 + TokenPositionEncoding512
Stage2_out = layer_normalization(multihead_attention(Stage1_out) + Stage1_out)
Stage3_out = layer_normalization(FFN(Stage2_out) + Stage2_out)

out_enc = Stage3_out
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4 id=decoder&gt;Decoder&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#decoder&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decoder’s architecture is similar however, it employs additional layer in &lt;em&gt;Stage 3&lt;/em&gt; with mask multi-head attention over encoder output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Stage 1 – Decoder input&lt;/strong&gt;
The input is the &lt;em&gt;output embedding&lt;/em&gt;, offset by one position to ensure that the prediction for position &lt;span class=math&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is only dependent on positions previous to/less than &lt;span class=math&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Stage 2 Masked Multi-head attention&lt;/strong&gt;
Modified to prevent positions to attend to subsequent positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stages 2, 3 and 4 also use the residual connection followed by normalization layer at its output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The details of each mechanism applied in the mentioned layers is more elaborated in following section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put together decoder works as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=highlight&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Stage1_out = OutputEmbedding512 + TokenPositionEncoding512

Stage2_Mask = masked_multihead_attention(Stage1_out)
Stage2_Norm1 = layer_normalization(Stage2_Mask) + Stage1_out
Stage2_Multi = multihead_attention(Stage2_Norm1 + out_enc) +  Stage2_Norm1
Stage2_Norm2 = layer_normalization(Stage2_Multi) + Stage2_Multi

Stage3_FNN = FNN(Stage2_Norm2)
Stage3_Norm = layer_normalization(Stage3_FNN) + Stage2_Norm2

out_dec = Stage3_Norm
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3 id=mechanisms-used-to-compose-transformer-architecture&gt;Mechanisms used to compose Transformer architecture&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#mechanisms-used-to-compose-transformer-architecture&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are couple types of layers that transformer consists of. Their details are depict in following sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=positional-encoding-pe&gt;Positional Encoding – PE&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#positional-encoding-pe&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In RNN (LSTM), the notion of time step is encoded in the sequence as inputs/outputs flow one at a time. In FNN, the &lt;em&gt;positional encoding&lt;/em&gt; must be preserved to represent the time in some way to preserve the &lt;em&gt;positional encoding&lt;/em&gt;. In case of the Transformer authors propose to encode time as &lt;span class=math&gt;\(sine\)&lt;/span&gt; wave, as an added extra input. Such signal is added to inputs and outputs to represent time passing&lt;sup id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-2-back&gt;&lt;a title="It is interesting how this resembles the brain waves and neural oscillations." class=simple-footnote href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-2&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, adding positional encodings to the input embeddings is a quite interesting topic. One way is to embed the absolute position of input elements (as in ConvS2S). However, authors use "sine and cosine functions of different frequencies". The "sinusoidal" version is quite complicated, while giving similar performance to the absolute position version. The crux is however, that it may allow the model to produce better translation on longer sentences at test time (at least longer than the sentences in the training data). This way sinusoidal method allows the model to extrapolate to longer sequence lengths&lt;sup id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-3-back&gt;&lt;a title="It reminds a bit the Pointer Networks that address similar problem" class=simple-footnote href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-3&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This encoding gives the model a sense of which portion of the sequence of the input (or output) it is currently dealing with. The positional encoding can be learned, or fixed. Authors made tests  (PPL, BLEU) showing that both: learned and fixed positional encodings perform similarly.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In paper authors have decided on fixed variant using &lt;span class=math&gt;\(sin\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=math&gt;\(cos\)&lt;/span&gt; functions to enable the network to learn information about tokens relative positions to the sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=math&gt;$$ \begin{eqnarray} PE_{(pos,2i)} = sin(pos/10000^{2i/d_{model}}) \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=math&gt;$$ \begin{eqnarray} PE_{(pos,2i+1)} = cos(pos/10000^{2i/d_{model}})\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course authors motivate the use of sinusoidal functions due to enabling model to generalize to sequences longer than ones encountered during training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=attention&gt;Attention&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#attention&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attention between encoder and decoder is crucial in NMT. Authors formulate the definition of &lt;em&gt;attention&lt;/em&gt; that has already been elaborated in &lt;a href="../../../../2017/Sep/01/Primer-NN/#attention-basis"&gt;Attention primer&lt;/a&gt;. Attention is a function that maps the 2-element input (&lt;em&gt;query&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;key-value&lt;/em&gt; pairs) to an output. The output given by the mapping function is a weighted sum of the &lt;em&gt;values&lt;/em&gt;. Where weights for each &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;  measures how much each input &lt;em&gt;key&lt;/em&gt; interacts with (or answers) the &lt;em&gt;query&lt;/em&gt;. While the attention is a goal for many research, the novelty about transformer attention is that it is &lt;strong&gt;multi-head  self-attention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=scaled-dot-product-attention&gt;Scaled Dot-Product Attention&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#scaled-dot-product-attention&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of encoder-decoder, the &lt;strong&gt;query&lt;/strong&gt; is usually the hidden state of the &lt;em&gt;decoder&lt;/em&gt;. Whereas &lt;strong&gt;key&lt;/strong&gt;, is the hidden state of the &lt;em&gt;encoder&lt;/em&gt;, and the corresponding &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; is normalized weight, representing how much attention a &lt;em&gt;key&lt;/em&gt; gets.  Output is calculated as a wighted sum – here the dot product of &lt;em&gt;query&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;key&lt;/em&gt; is used to get a &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is assumed that &lt;em&gt;queries&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;keys&lt;/em&gt; are of &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_k\)&lt;/span&gt; dimension and &lt;em&gt;values&lt;/em&gt; are of &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_v\)&lt;/span&gt; dimension. Those dimensions are imposed by the linear projection discussed in the multi-head attention section. The  input is represented by three matrices: queries’ matrix &lt;span class=math&gt;\(Q\)&lt;/span&gt;, keys’ matrix &lt;span class=math&gt;\(K\)&lt;/span&gt; and values’ matrix &lt;span class=math&gt;\(V\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;compatibility function&lt;/em&gt; (see &lt;a href="../../../../2017/Sep/01/Primer-NN/#attention-basis"&gt;Attention primer&lt;/a&gt;)  is considered in terms of two, &lt;em&gt;additive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;multiplicative&lt;/em&gt; (dot-product) variants &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.0473"&gt;Bahdanau et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt; with similar theoretical complexity. However, the dot-product (&lt;span class=math&gt;\(q \cdot  k = \sum_{i=1}^{d_k}q_i k_i\)&lt;/span&gt;) with scaling factor &lt;span class=math&gt;\(1/\sqrt{d_k}\)&lt;/span&gt; is chosen due to being much faster and space-efficient, as it uses  optimized matrix multiplication code&lt;sup id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-4-back&gt;&lt;a title="The additional scaling factor is advised for large \(d_k\) where dot product grow large in magnitude, as softmax is suspected to be pushed to vanishing gradient area, thus making the additive attention perform better. " class=simple-footnote href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-4&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=math&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray} Attention (Q,K,V) = softmax \Big( \frac{QK^T}{\sqrt{d_k}} \Big) V \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using NumPy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=highlight&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=k&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=nf&gt;attention&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;Q&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;V&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=n&gt;num&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=o&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=o&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;dot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;Q&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=o&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=n&gt;denum&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=o&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=o&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;sqrt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=o&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=mi&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=k&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=o&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;dot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;softmax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=n&gt;num&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=o&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;denum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=n&gt;V&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=p&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4 id=multi-head-attention&gt;Multi-head attention&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#multi-head-attention&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformer reduces the number of operations required to relate (especially distant) positions in input and output sequence to a &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(1)\)&lt;/span&gt;. However, this comes at cost of reduced effective resolution because of averaging attention-weighted positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img src="https://mchromiak.github.io/articles/2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/img/MultiHead.png" alt="Multihead attetntion"&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Figure 3. Multi-Head Attention consists of &lt;span class=math&gt;\(h\)&lt;/span&gt; attention layers running in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reduce this cost authors propose the multi-head attention:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=math&gt;\(h=8\)&lt;/span&gt; attention layers (aka “heads”): that represent linear projection (for the purpose of dimension reduction) of key &lt;span class=math&gt;\(K\)&lt;/span&gt; and query &lt;span class=math&gt;\(Q\)&lt;/span&gt; into &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_k\)&lt;/span&gt;-dimension and value &lt;span class=math&gt;\(V\)&lt;/span&gt; into &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_v\)&lt;/span&gt;- dimension:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=math&gt;$$head_i = Attention(Q W^Q_i, K W^K_i, V W^V_i) , i=1,\dots,h$$&lt;/div&gt;
where projections are parameter matrices &lt;span class=math&gt;\(W^Q_i, W^K_i\in\mathbb{R}^{d_{model}\times d_k}, W^V_i\in\mathbb{R}^{d_{model}\times d_v}\)&lt;/span&gt;,
for &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_k=d_v=d_{model}/h = 64\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;scaled-dot attention applied in parallel on each layer (different linear projections of &lt;span class=math&gt;\(k, q, v\)&lt;/span&gt;) results in &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_v\)&lt;/span&gt;-dimensional output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;concatenate outputs of each layer (different linear projection; also referred as &lt;em&gt;”head”&lt;/em&gt;): &lt;span class=math&gt;\(Concat(head_1,\dots,head_h)\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;linearly project the concatenation result form the previous step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=math&gt;$$ MultiHeadAttention(Q,K,V) = Concat(head_1,\dots,head_h) W^O$$&lt;/div&gt;
where  &lt;span class=math&gt;\(W^0\in\mathbb{R}^{d_{hd_v}\times d_{model}}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformer use multi-head (&lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_{model}/h\)&lt;/span&gt; parallel attention functions) attention instead of single (&lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_{model}\)&lt;/span&gt;-dimensional) attention function (i.e. &lt;span class=math&gt;\(q,k,v\)&lt;/span&gt; all &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_{model}\)&lt;/span&gt;-dimensional). It is at similar computational cost as in the case of single-head attention due to reduced dimensions of each head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformer imitates the classical attention mechanism (known e.g. from &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.0473"&gt;Bahdanau et al., 2014&lt;/a&gt; or Conv2S2) where in encoder-decoder attention layers &lt;em&gt;queries&lt;/em&gt; are form previous decoder layer, and the (memory) &lt;em&gt;keys&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;values&lt;/em&gt; are from output of the encoder.  Therefore, each position in decoder can attend over all positions in the input sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=self-attention-sa&gt;Self-Attention (SA)&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#self-attention-sa&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="../../../../2017/Sep/01/Primer-NN/#attention-basis"&gt;Attention Primer&lt;/a&gt; for basics on attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;encoder&lt;/em&gt;, self-attention layers process input &lt;span class=math&gt;\(queries, keys\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=math&gt;\(values\)&lt;/span&gt; that comes form same place i.e. the output of previous layer in encoder. Each position in encoder can attend to all positions from previous layer of the encoder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;decoder&lt;/em&gt;, self-attention layer enable each position to attend to all previous positions in the decoder, including the current position. To preserve auto-regressive property, the leftward information flow is presented inside the dot-product attention by masking out (set to &lt;span class=math&gt;\(- \infty\)&lt;/span&gt;) all &lt;span class=math&gt;\(values\)&lt;/span&gt; that are input for softmax which correspond to this illegal connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authors motivates the use of self-attention layers instead of recurrent or convolutional layers with three desiderata:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimize total computational complexity per layer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pros:&lt;/strong&gt; self-attention layers connects all positions with &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(1)\)&lt;/span&gt; number of sequentially executed operations (eg. vs &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(n)\)&lt;/span&gt; in RNN)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maximize amount of parallelizable computations, measured by minimum number of sequential operations required&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pros:&lt;/strong&gt; for sequence length &lt;span class=math&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt; &amp;lt; representation dimensionality &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d\)&lt;/span&gt; (true for SOTA sequence representation models like &lt;em&gt;word-piece, byte-pair&lt;/em&gt;). For very long sequences &lt;span class=math&gt;\(n&amp;gt;d\)&lt;/span&gt; self-attention can consider only neighborhood of some size &lt;span class=math&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt;  in the input sequence centered around the respective output position, thus increasing the max path length to &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(n/r)\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimize maximum path length between any two input and output positions in network composed of the different layer types . The shorter the path between any combination of positions in the input and output sequences, the easier to learn long-range dependencies. (See why &lt;a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.24.7321"&gt;Hochreiter et al, 2001&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=position-wise-ffn&gt;Position-wise FFN&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#position-wise-ffn&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In encoder and decoder the attention sublayers is being processed by a fully connected FNN. It is applied to each position separately and identically meaning two linear transformations and a ReLU
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=math&gt;$$ FFN(x) = max(0, xW_1+b_1) W_2 + b_2$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Linear transformations are the same for each position, but use different parameters from layer to layer. It works similarly to two convolutions of kernel size 1. The input/output dimension is &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_{model}=512\)&lt;/span&gt; while inner0layer is &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_{ff}=2048\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=pseudocode-or-flowchart-description-of-the-algorithm&gt;Pseudocode or flowchart description of the algorithm.&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#pseudocode-or-flowchart-description-of-the-algorithm&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img src="https://mchromiak.github.io/articles/2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/img/transform20fps.gif" alt="Transformer  "&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Figure 4. Transformer step-by-step sequence transduction in form of English-to-French translation. Adopted from &lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2017/08/transformer-novel-neural-network.html"&gt;Google Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In encoder phase (shown in the Figure 1.), transformer first generates initial representation/embedding for each word in input sentence (empty circle). Next, for each word, self-attention aggregates information form all other words in context of sentence, and creates new representation (filled circles). The process is repeated for each word in sentence. Successively building new representations, based on previous ones is repeated multiple times and in parallel for each word (next layers of filled circles).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decoder acts similarly generating one word at a time in a left-to-right-pattern. It attends to previously generated words of decoder and final representation of encoder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that this self-attention strategy allows to face the issue of &lt;strong&gt;coreference resolution&lt;/strong&gt; where e.g. word “&lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt;” in a sentence can refer to different noun of the sentence depending on context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img src="https://mchromiak.github.io/articles/2017/Sep/12/Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need/img/CoreferenceResolution.png" alt="coreference resolution"&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Figure 5. Co-reference resolution. The &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; in both cases relates to different token. Adopted from &lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2017/08/transformer-novel-neural-network.html"&gt;Google Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=heuristics-or-rules-of-thumb&gt;Heuristics or rules of thumb.&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#heuristics-or-rules-of-thumb&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authors have conducted a series of tests (Table 3 of the paper) where they discuss recommendation of &lt;span class=math&gt;\(N=6\)&lt;/span&gt; layers with model size 512 based on &lt;span class=math&gt;\(h=8\)&lt;/span&gt; heads with key, values dimensions of 64 using 100K steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also stated that dot-product compatibility function might be further optimized due to model quality is decreased with smaller &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_k\)&lt;/span&gt; (row B).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed, fixed sinusoidal positional encodings are claimed to produce nearly equal score comparing to learned positional encodings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=what-classes-of-problem-is-the-algorithm-well-suited&gt;What classes of problem is the algorithm well suited?&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#what-classes-of-problem-is-the-algorithm-well-suited&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sequence transduction (language translation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;classic language analysis task of syntactic constituency parsing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;different inputs and outputs modalities, such as images and video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;coreference resolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=common-benchmark-or-example-datasets-used-to-demonstrate-the-algorithm&gt;Common benchmark or example datasets used to demonstrate the algorithm.&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#common-benchmark-or-example-datasets-used-to-demonstrate-the-algorithm&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perplexity (PPL) BLEU&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English-to-German translation development set WMT 2014 English-to-German and WMT 2014
English-to-French translation tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;newstest2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English constituency parsing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=useful-resources-for-learning-more-about-the-algorithm&gt;Useful resources for learning more about the algorithm.&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#useful-resources-for-learning-more-about-the-algorithm&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2017/08/transformer-novel-neural-network.html"&gt;Google blog post1&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2017/06/accelerating-deep-learning-research.html"&gt;Google blog post2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some more general learning open-source software frameworks for NMT:
&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/nmt"&gt;Tensorflow: Neural Machine Translation (seq2seq) Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
Ground-up explaining NMT concepts tutorial with code, based on Tensorflow by Google Research. Based on &lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2017/07/building-your-own-neural-machine.html"&gt;Google Research blog.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/facebookresearch/fairseq"&gt;Torch: FirSeq&lt;/a&gt; seq2seq and ConvS2S from Facebook AI.
* &lt;a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tensor2tensor"&gt;Tensorflow: Tensor2Tensor&lt;/a&gt; From used by Transformer authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=thoughts-on-the-idea&gt;Thoughts on the idea.&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#thoughts-on-the-idea&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my limited knowledge there are some statements that might benefit form more explanation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the scaling factor (Equation 3) makes an impact?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How actually the &lt;strong&gt;positional encoding&lt;/strong&gt; work? Why they have chosen the sin/cos functions and why the position and dimension are in this relation? Finally how sinusoidal helps translate long sentences?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does having separate position-wise FFNs help? (comparing to ConvS2S).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;“cost of reduced effective resolution due to averaging attention-weighted position”&lt;/em&gt; is claimed to be a motivation for multi-head attention. How to understand better what is the issue and how multi-head attention helps?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Transformer brings a significantly improvement over ConvS2S, but where does the improvement come from? It is not clear from the work. ConvS2S lacks the self-attention, is it what brings the advantage?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masked Attention. The problem of using same parts of input on different decoding step is claimed to be solved by penalizing (mask-out to &lt;span class=math&gt;\(-\infty\)&lt;/span&gt;) input tokens that have obtained high attention scores in the past decoding steps – a bit vague. How does it work? Maybe explicitly having a position-wise FFN automatically fixes that problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applying multi-head attention might improve performance due to better parallelization. However, Table 3 also show increasing &lt;span class=math&gt;\(h=1 to 8\)&lt;/span&gt; improves accuracy. Why? Moving  &lt;span class=math&gt;\(h\)&lt;/span&gt; to 16 or 32 is not that beneficial. How to interpret this correctly?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How important the autoregression is in context of this architecture?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please leave a comment if you have any other question, or would like to get more explanation on any of the paper’s particularities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=primary-references-or-resources-in-which-the-algorithm-was-first-described&gt;Primary references or resources in which the algorithm was first described.&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#primary-references-or-resources-in-which-the-algorithm-was-first-described&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paper: &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03762"&gt;ArXiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=some-interesting-future-research&gt;Some interesting future research&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#some-interesting-future-research&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Devising more sophisticated compatibility function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase maximum path length to &lt;span class=math&gt;\(O(n/r)\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class=math&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; would be only a neighborhood size of positions to be considered by self-attention instead of all positions in sequence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4 id=references&gt;References:&lt;a title="Permanent link" class=headerlink href=#references&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;ol class=simple-footnotes&gt;&lt;li id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-1&gt;While applying dimensionality reduction techniques (e.g. PCA, t-SNE) on embeddings, the outcome plot gathers the semantically close sentences  together &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.3215"&gt;Sutskever et al., 2014&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=simple-footnote-back href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-1-back&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-2&gt;It is interesting how this resembles the brain waves and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neural_oscillation"&gt;neural oscillations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=simple-footnote-back href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-2-back&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-3&gt;It reminds a bit the Pointer Networks that address similar problem &lt;a class=simple-footnote-back href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-3-back&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-4&gt;The additional scaling factor is advised for large &lt;span class=math&gt;\(d_k\)&lt;/span&gt; where dot product grow large in magnitude, as softmax is suspected to be pushed to vanishing gradient area, thus making the additive attention perform better.  &lt;a class=simple-footnote-back href=#sf-Transformer-Attention-is-all-you-need-4-back&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="NMT"></category><category term="transformer"></category><category term="Sequence transduction"></category><category term="Attention model"></category><category term="Machine translation"></category><category term="seq2seq"></category><category term="NLP"></category></entry></feed>